Okay, we finished yesterday in the discussion if you recall, a group
of people or a person who was known as דבי רב Dvei
Rav or בי רב Bei Rav had said that רב Rav פוסק
paskens like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose in two cases: the case of
the hermaphrodite that we've been talking about, the אנדרוגינוס, Androgynos, and the
case of the grafting, the הרכבה, Harkava, which we also saw the
example of that. And then we saw that we had a statement
in the name of שמואל Shmuel that in the case of a
woman who is bleeding because of contractions or something like that in
relation to her
pregnancy,
and whether or not that is a case of זוב, zov, שמואל
Shmuel פוסק paskens like רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, and he also פוסק
paskens that way in the case of קידוש, Kiddush, which we're going
to learn what that is right now. So we heard about the
case of יולדת בזוב Yoledet Bezov where רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose said,
I believe that she had, that anything within two weeks is still
reasonable to say that it's related to her contractions, but more than
that we assume that that's really a case of זיבה. zivah. קידוש,
Kiddush, we're four lines from the end on פ"ג עמוד א'. 83
Amud Aleph. קידוש דתנן המסכך גפנו על גבי תבואתו של חברו
הרי זה קידש וחייב באחריותו דברי רבי מאיר.
Kiddush ditnan
hamisakech gafno al gabei tevuato shel chaveiro harei ze kideish vechayav be'achrayuto
divrei Rabbi Meir. Somebody whose vine is planted in his field, but
in some way he manages to prop it up so that it
is hanging over the grain crop of his fellow has created a
situation of כלאי הכרם, Kil'ei HaKerem, of a vine that's mixed up
with
other kinds of species, and that's אסור, asur, you have to burn
it. We call it קידש, kideish, it's not actually, we don't say
אסור, asur, we say that it's become holy, you're not allowed to
eat it, you're not allowed to get any kind of benefit from
it, you need to burn it. So the problem is that this
fellow did this with his partner with another person's field. He
didn't actually plant a vine in it, he just moved his vine
so that it was overhanging, overhanging this field.
So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that's it, he has to burn
it and he has to pay
for the other fellow's losses. רבי יוסי ורבי שמעון אומרים אין אדם
אוסר דבר שאינו שלו.
Rabbi Yose veRabbi
Shimon omrim ein adam oseir davar she'eino shelo. A person is not
able to create a situation of כלאי הכרם Kil'ei HaKerem on somebody
else's field.
Strictly speaking, what he says is a person
is not able to make something אסור asur that does not belong
to him. So this is an interesting view on כלאי הכרם Kil'ei
HaKerem on the idea of כלאים, kilayim, that somehow although we assume
that כלאים kilayim is actually about
a state of being, that you have two different kinds of plants
in one place, at the end of the day,
at
the end of the day,
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say, yes that's
true, but it also has to be yours. You can't just go
around making other people's fields קודש. kodesh.
איבעיא להו. Iba'iya lehu. It was asked in the בית מדרש Beit
Midrash of the אמוראים. Amoraim. אנדרוגינוס מה
לי אמר שמואל? Androgynos ma li amar Shmuel? So we heard בי
רב Bei Rav say, we know that there's a מחלוקת, machloket, sorry,
we heard בי רב Bei Rav say that רב Rav פוסק paskens
like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose by אנדרוגינוס Androgynos and by הרכבה,
Harkava, by grafting. But what does שמואל Shmuel say?
So we say תא שמע דאמר
שמואל לרב ענן ליתא לברייתא מקמי מתניתין.
Ta shema de'amar Shmuel leRav Anan
leita livraita mikamei matnitin. שמואל Shmuel said the ברייתא Baraita does not
stand in the face of the משנה. Mishna. The ברייתא, Baraita, what
was the ברייתא Baraita we said that didn't stand in the face
of the משנה? Mishna? The ברייתא Baraita was the ברייתא Baraita that
said that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose holds that an אנדרוגינוס Androgynos is,
well, depends how you understand it, but he says an אנדרוגינוס Androgynos
is בריה בפני עצמה, birya bifnei atzma, its own category, and it
is not, the חכמים Chachamim never said if it was a man
or a woman. Now I'll just point out because I didn't say
it yesterday that there's a long תוספות Tosafot on this, this is
quite an interesting question of is the אנדרוגינוס Androgynos simply a ספק
safek that the חכמים Chachamim never actually developed, or is the אנדרוגינוס
Androgynos a third kind of option, a different category?
What's that?
Isn't that the גמרא?
Gemara? So the גמרא... Gemara... The גמרא Gemara seems to have a
question between whether the אנדרוגינוס Androgynos is a זכר, zachar, which seems
to be the position of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer in the משנה, Mishnah,
and whether it might, I mean it's unclear what it means in
the ברייתא. Braitah. In the ברייתא Braitah where רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
says בריה בפני עצמה, biryah bifnei atzmah, it could be בריה בפני
עצמה biryah bifnei atzmah that it's an unverified ספק safek or בריה
בפני עצמה biryah bifnei atzmah its own thing. The תוספות Tosafos tend
to go in the direction of saying that an אנדרוגינוס Androgynos is
a, in this position in this particular ברייתא, Braitah, means בריה בפני
עצמה עצמה ממש, biryah bifnei atzmah atzmah mamash, meaning that it really
is a third category, a third gender that isn't included neither in
זכר zachar nor נקבה, nekeivah, and they say but there are places
where the משנה Mishnah treats the אנדרוגינוס Androgynos as an actual ספק.
safek. So we're still kind of in this question. In any case,
שמואל Shmuel פוסק'נס paskens that the משנה Mishnah stands in the face
of the ברייתא, Braitah,
which makes it sound like שמואל Shmuel פוסק'נס paskens like רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose in the משנה. Mishnah. I have to point out that
just because the ברייתא Braitah doesn't stand in the face of the
משנה, Mishnah, that could be שמואל'ס Shmuel's statement that okay well
רבי יוסי'ס Rabbi Yose's final statement was in the משנה, Mishnah, not
in the ברייתא. Braitah. It doesn't necessarily mean that he's פוסק'נינג paskening
that way, but at the same time why would he be evaluating
which רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is the authoritative רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
if he didn't really hold that that was the הלכה. halacha. הרכבה
מה לי אמר שמואל, Harkavah
mah li
amar Shmuel, what about in the case of grafting? What did שמואל
Shmuel say there? תא שמע, Tashma, דאמר ליה
שמואל לרב ענן, de'amar lei Shmuel leRav Anan, another statement of שמואל
Shmuel to רב
ענן, Rav Anan, תני כמאן דאמר שלושה ושלושים. tanei keman de'amar sheloshah
ushloshim.
So
when we give over our ברייתא Braitah with regard to the grafting,
if you recall the grafting case was the statement that you can't
graft thirty days before the beginning of the שמיטה shemitah year.
And we said and somebody said well actually all you need is
three days before the שמיטה shemitah year. And רב נחמן Rav Nachman
so that was רבי יהודה בן בתירה Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira I
think, and רב נחמן Rav Nachman said on this what we're talking
about is not three days immediately before the שמיטה shemitah year but
actually three days or thirty days or maybe two weeks according to
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon before the month
cushion that we give to the שמיטה shemitah year. In other words
we're talking about in the month of
תמוז Tammuz when you're allowed to graft or not, not in the
month of אלול. Elul. In אלול Elul everybody agrees that you're not
allowed to do any of these certain kinds of agricultural work, but
how much time do you need to give, how much cushion do
you need to give so that the graft is not still taking
root during חודש אלול? Chodesh Elul? Yeah.
Why is the grafting in this whole discussion?
What's the connection? So it has to do with the way that
the תלמוד Talmud gets organized. The תלמוד Talmud has a lot of
organizational principles, but one is to create a list of פסקים. psakim.
Remember and it goes back to what we're talking about with Dov
yesterday. If I understand your question correctly, my understanding of your question
is we're talking about an אנדרוגינוס, Androgynos, where did grafting get into
this? So I was talking, Dov asked yesterday well what about isn't
the משנה Mishnah written down and so on and I was saying
that all of this is actually oral texts. Oral texts you need
to come up with strategies for how you're going to remember them.
One of the ways you remember them is you say oh רב
Rav holds that the הלכה halacha is like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
in the following three cases. And they're three totally separate cases, but
we know we keep them in mind because רב Rav holds that
the הלכה halacha is that way. And then we say oh and
שמואל Shmuel holds that the הלכה halacha is like רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose and then we have two more cases that don't have anything
to do with אנדרוגינוס, Androgynos, at least in רב'ס Rav's case one
of them was אנדרוגינוס, Androgynos, right? What I can also point out
and I think the תוספות Tosafos or רש"י Rashi pointed out here
is that in every place where we in these cases where רב
Rav פוסק'נס paskens like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and שמואל Shmuel also
פוסק'נס paskens like רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, it's all רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon together. I don't know if you
noticed that when we're discussing it, but these are not simply cases
of רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, these are also cases where רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon are a pair. Yeah, one
second. So that being the case these cases are actually much more
closely connected to our case of the hermaphrodite than we might have
thought if it had simply been a case of רבי יוסי. Rabbi
Yose. Yeah, Charlie?
Yeah, generally in a dispute between רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and any
of his contemporaries we follow רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. Yeah. And it
looks like שמואל'ס Shmuel's not doing that and also why would there
be a question if that rule was established in the time of
the תנאים? Tannaim?
It's a good question. First of
all
I have no idea that that rule's necessarily established in the time
of the תנאים Tannaim or even in the early אמוראים Amoraim like
רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. I mean those rules tend to be
later. My understanding is Is that I haven't read his work, but
Professor Jonathan Milgram has written quite a bit on the rules of
פסיקה Pesika and when they come from and what the rule how
what those rules are.
But yeah, it's a it's a good question in terms of what's
going on here.
In any case, the case of grafting, שמואל Shmuel פוסק paskens like
the one who says it takes three days for a graft to
take root. Therefore, you need to if your last grafting before the
שמיטה Shmita year needs to be at least three days before the
end of the month of תמוז Tamuz so that it doesn't get
into the month of אלול Elul before the שמיטה Shmita year.
So now we've gone through שמואל, Shmuel, what about
רב? Rav? קושי
מאי אמר רב? Koshi mai amar Rav? What about רב's Rav position
in קושי Koshi in the case of a woman who is bleeding
and does her is her bleeding associated with her contractions or not?
תיקו. Teku. We simply don't know. We don't know what רב's Rav
position is on that. קידוש מאי אמר רב? Kiddush mai amar Rav?
In the case of the the vine that is hanging over the
field, what is the position of רב? Rav? אמר רב יוסף, Amar
Rav Yosef, תא שמע ta shema דאמר רב הונא אמר רב, de'amar
Rav Huna amar Rav, אין הלכה כרבי יוסי. ein halacha ke'Rabbi Yose.
So רב יוסף Rav Yosef has a has a tradition that the
הלכה halacha is not like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose according to רב
Rav in this in this situation. אמר ליה אביי, Amar leh Abaye,
אביי Abaye is רב יוסף's Rav Yosef student, and he says to
him, מאי חזית דסמכת הא? mai chazita desamachta ha? Why are you
focusing on that ברייתא? braita? סמוך הא? smocha ha? Rely on this
other ברייתא, braita, sorry not ברייתא, braita, this other מימרא, memra, this
other statement of the אמוראים, Amora'im, דאמר רב אדא אמר רב, de'amar
Rav Ada amar Rav, הלכה כרבי יוסי. halacha ke'Rabbi Yose.
We have a tradition that רב אדא Rav Ada said in the
name of רב Rav that הלכה halacha is like רבי יוסי. Rabbi
Yose. So now we're a little stuck. We have one tradition that
says that רב Rav doesn't פוסק pasken like רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose,
another tradition that says that רב Rav does פוסק pasken like רבי
יוסי. Rabbi Yose.
אמרי, Amrei, בי רב מנו? Bei Rav manu? When it's said, remember
that the people who said רב Rav פוסק paskens like רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose in these cases, it was said for by a person
or people who are called בי רב, Bei Rav, the house of
רב. Rav. So who are those people? בי רב מנו, Bei Rav
manu, who are they? רב הונא. Rav Huna. That that בי רב
Bei Rav that we were talking about before that was giving this
tradition is רב הונא. Rav Huna. ורב הונא אמר אין הלכה. Ve'Rav
Huna amar ein halacha. So according to the tradition of which we
started, which said that רב Rav פוסק paskens like רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose in these cases, that same tradition says that רב Rav doesn't
פוסק pasken like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose in the case of קידוש
הכרם. Kiddush Hakerem.
And that's why we choose to to privilege רב הונא Rav Huna
over רב אדא. Rav Ada.
רבי יהודה אומר טומטום וכולי. Rabbi Yehuda omer tumtum vechulu. If you
remember back in our משנה Mishna on פ"א ע"א, Pe Alef Amud
Alef, רבי יהודה אומר טומטום שנקרא ונמצא זכר לא יחלוץ מפני שהוא
כסריס. Rabbi Yehuda omer tumtum shenikra venimtza zachar lo yachlotz mipnei shehu
kesaris. A טומטום tumtum who is this person with undifferentiated genitalia, but
there is a sense that somehow
if something called קריאה kria could happen, I don't know, it seems
to be that there's like a membrane of skin or something concealing
the genitalia or something like that. But if that membrane were somehow
ruptured that we would be able
to
see whether what
whether it's a man or a woman. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said
back in our משנה Mishna that if the טומטום tumtum has this
had this thing happens, the rupture the the the skin tears in
some way and you're able to see whether what whether it's a
man or a woman, it turns out to be a man, he
shouldn't do חליצה chalitza because he is a סריס, saris, he or
he is like a סריס, saris, that's what he says, כסריס. kesaris.
That because he is similar to a סריס, saris, he is פטור
patur from יבום yibum and therefore he also can't do חליצה. chalitza.
אמר רבי אמי. Amar Rabbi Ami. רבי אמי Rabbi Ami said about
this,
מאי עביד ליה רבי יהודה לטומטום דבירי דאותבוה אהי כורסיה ואיקרא ואוליד
שבע בנין? mai avid leh Rabbi Yehuda letumtum debirei de'otvuha ahi kursei
veikra veolid sheva banin?
So what would רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda do with this famous טומטום
tumtum of בירי Birei from this place that they sat him on
a particular kind of chair, maybe a chair that is special for
this operation, it's not clear exactly what kind of chair. It's not
clear exactly what kind of a chair they're talking about, and this
rupturing took place, and they figured out that it was a
man, והוליד שבעה בנין, v'olid sheva banin, and
he had seven children. So how are you going to say that
he's like a eunuch?
He is, he's clearly fertile.
ורבי יהודה אמר לך, v'Rabbi Yehuda amar lach, so what's the answer?
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would say to you: חזור על בניו מאין
הם. chazor al banav me'ayin hem. Check his wife carefully, you'll find
that she hasn't been faithful, that these sons are not from, are
not his, are not his children. תניא, Tanya, רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
אומר:
Rabbi Yose
b'Rabbi Yehuda omer: טומטום לא יחלוץ tumtum lo yachlotz שמא יקרע ונמצא
סריס חמה.
shema yikara v'nimtza
saris chama. One second,
yes.
So
we
have, in generally speaking, we assume for reasons of חזקה, Chazaka, I
think, that a married couple, the children belong to, are belong to
the husband, right?
The children belong to, oh you mean we have a חזקה, Chazaka,
yes.
But and here we're challenging that חזקה. Chazaka.
Well, except for that it's a case of a טומטום. tumtum. In
other words, once you have, once your חזקה, Chazaka, once you're no
longer dealing with a standard case, you're dealing with somebody who you
believe in most cases would be, I mean, he seems to think
in all cases is actually a eunuch, right?
So חזקה Chazaka doesn't, so yeah, you're no longer, you're not going
to hold with a חזקה Chazaka of somebody who's known to be
infertile then has some kind of miraculous, starts being miraculously
fertile.
So it doesn't challenge the basis of the חזקה?
Chazaka? No, I don't think so.
The חזקה Chazaka has exceptions.
Yes, that's right.
I mean, you have exceptions that we just ignore.
We assume, yeah, we assume that what we're going with in the
case of the חזקה Chazaka is a standard case. A טומטום שנקרא
tumtum she'nikra is not a standard case. Charlie?
And so yes, was it yesterday or the day before? I forget
which one it was. We had the case where you had two
barrels and they fell into two and we assume that they were
still separate and everything was okay.
Which is unlikely in most cases and here we're taking something and
assuming the worst as opposed to yesterday when we did the best.
So yesterday we're talking about a case of ספק. safek. In this
case, it looks to me like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda doesn't think
that we're in a case of ספק. safek. He really believes medical
fact that טומטומים tumtums are sterile. And therefore there's nothing really to
talk about, right? And you say, oh what would he do with
the, with this extraneous case, outlier? And he would say, actually he
wouldn't say outlier, what he would say
is check it, you'll find that it's not an outlier, that something
has happened here that everybody was, you know, was nice of you
all to think of this case as a,
you know, to think the best of this man's wife, but this
man cannot give birth, it's simple medical fact, this man, sorry, no
man can give birth, this man cannot father children, and so whatever's
going on, it's not from him.
Now we have a case of רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, Rabbi Yose
b'Rabbi Yehuda, the son of רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יוסי. Rabbi
Yose. It's always interesting, you know that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva had
five major students: רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, and רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar.
And they all named their children after one another. So you have
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon, רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda.
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose himself didn't name, didn't name any student, he
didn't name his son, he named him ישמעאל. Yishmael.
Anyway, it's sweet that they named after one another. So this is
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda, and he says, apparently
in the footsteps of his father,
טומטום לא יחלוץ. tumtum lo yachlotz. A טומטום tumtum who has not
been verified should not do חליצה. chalitza. שמא יקרע ונמצא סריס חמה,
shema yikara v'nimtza saris chama, in case he is,
this operation happens on him and we find out that he is
a natural
eunuch, meaning a person whose sexual organs did not fully develop.
So
if
that were the case, what we would find out is that the
חליצה chalitza that he did is not real חליצה, chalitza, and that
this woman who's now gone and gotten married actually got married against
the זיקה zika that she has to the other brothers, if there
are other brothers. So I
mean
that it's not necessarily the case that he would be a סריס
חמה.
saris chama. But it might be the case that he's a סריס
חמה, saris chama, because of that we don't let him do חליצה.
chalitza. So we say אטו כל דמקרע זכר הוי? atu kol d'mikarei
zachar havei? Said: wait, is this really the thing you have to
be concerned about, that he's going to be a סריס חמה, saris
chama, that he's going to be some kind of natural eunuch? What
our main concern with a טומטום tumtum is that they might end
up being a woman, right? That's what you figure
out with a טומטום.
tumtum. Is it a man or a woman? woman, so what? What's
that?
And there's no problem with זיקה. zika.
Okay, so well, so it depends. If there's, right, there's no problem
with זיקה zika if it's a,
if he's a סריס חמה saris chama either. The assumption here is
that there's a brother. Another brother. Right? There had, so right, what
are you going to do about the brother? That's the question. So
סריס חמה, saris chama, that's the most likely case you can come
up with with a טומטום tumtum who's been נקרע? nikra? ייבום yibum
with a woman wouldn't take effect anyway. Correct. But I still, but
it still means there's the זיקה. zika. So I didn't, I don't
think I clarified the case clearly enough. Here's what's happening. We have
a טומטום tumtum and we have another brother. Okay, we have actually
three, two brothers and a טומטום, tumtum, right? One brother died and
his wife now is a יבמה. yevama. Okay? Now the טומטום tumtum
should not do חליצה chalitza by her. Why not? Because what could
happen? The טומטום tumtum could end up being נקרע nikra and we
would find out that he's a eunuch. Eunuchs are not חייב chayav
in ייבום. yibum. And therefore his חליצה chalitza was nothing and therefore
she still has a זיקה zika to the second brother. However, the
גמרא Gemara says, wait a minute, סריס חמה, saris chama, a natural
eunuch, that's your concern? With a טומטום, tumtum, your concern shouldn't be
that it's a male סריס חמה, saris chama, your concern should be
that it's not even a male, that it's a woman. That and
clearly the,
yeah, clearly the חדא ועוד chada ve'od
and you go with the סריס חמה saris chama rather than going
with the נקבה? nekeivah?
That wouldn't make a difference.
Ah, so okay, maybe that's the way, maybe that's the direction the
גמרא Gemara is going to go. But at least initially, the גמרא
Gemara says, is that really what you think? So we say הכי
קאמר. hachi ka'amar. This is what he meant to say: שמא יקרע
ונמצא נקבה ואפילו נמצא זכר שמא ימצא סריס חמה. shema yikarei venimtzah
nekeivah ve'afilu nimtza zachar shema yimatzei saris chama. Just like you said.
מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu? What is the, is there a מחלוקת machloket
between רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה? Rabbi Yose
b'Rabbi Yehuda? רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said that a טומטום tumtum should,
a טומטום tumtum who
is
נקרע nikra shouldn't do חליצה. chalitza. Why not? Because every טומטום tumtum
is a סריס. saris.
So,
what about... but so what is the, what does רבי יוסי ברבי
יהודה Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda add in his suggestion?
Well, it depends how you take שמא יקרע ונמצא סריס חמה. shema
yikarei venimtza saris chama. Is it that for sure if it's a
male, it's a סריס חמה, saris chama, or if it's a male,
it could be a סריס חמה saris chama or it may not
be? In which case, in that other case before, the guy with
the seven kids, you would still say, you know, he could still
father kids.
Okay, so right, I mean we're going to, so that's exactly what
they're going to say. אמר רבא: Amar Rava: לפסול במקום אחין ולחלוץ
שלא במקום אחין איכא בינייהו. lifsol bemakom achin velachalotz shelo bemakom achin
ika beinaihu. So to make her פסולה psula to the other brothers
and to do חליצה chalitza in a case where there are no
brothers is the place of their מחלוקת. machloket. So what does that
mean? So he would say, I'm sorry, I need to review for
myself. לפסול במקום אחין. lifsol bemakom achin. רש״י Rashi says, אם יש
אחים שלמים עמו וחלץ לה טומטום לרבי יהודה דאמר שהוא כסריס מחזיק
ליה בסריס ודאי ולא פסלה אחין ומתייבמת ולרבי יוסי שמא קתני ספיקא
הוא ופסלה על האחים דילמא לאו סריס הוא והוה חליצה. im yesh
achim shleimim imo vechalatz lah tumtum le'Rabbi Yehuda de'amar shehu kesaris machzik
lei besaris vadai velo paslah achin umityabemet ul'Rabbi Yose shema katani sefeika
hu upaslah al ha'achin dilma lav saris hu vehavei chalitza.
So if he does do חליצה, chalitza, so רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
would say his חליצה chalitza is nothing, he's a סריס. saris. Even
if it turns out to be a male, he's still going to
be a סריס. saris. And therefore if one of the other brothers
wants to do ייבום, yibum, he can certainly do ייבום. yibum.
Whereas רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda would say no,
we're still in a case of ספק. safek. And therefore it's possible
that he is indeed a fertile male. We need to find out
if he's a סריס חמה saris chama or not. And therefore if
he does חליצה, chalitza, that would then prevent any of the
other brothers from doing ייבום yibum with her until we find out
what the truth is about this טומטום. tumtum.
How would you find out if he's a סריס חמה saris chama
or not?
Well, סריס חמה saris chama you can, is shriveled testicles. So I
think you can tell. You can tell once the טומטום tumtum is
נקרע, nikra, you can tell whether it is or not. But if
he's not נקרע? nikra? So if it's not נקרע, nikra, I don't
think you can ever find out. And then you have an עגונה.
agunah. I don't know, it's not such a terrible עגונה agunah as,
I mean, because she's only בלאו belav to the rest of the
world. But you know, it's still an issue. It's an issue. Yeah,
Charlie.
So if there's not another brother,
this woman can marry right away.
Okay, so now, so the question is what about, what about in
a case where there's not another brother?
Why can't you just say let him do חליצה? chalitza? What do
you lose? Unless she's getting married to a כהן Kohen or something.
So what you lose is that she becomes פסולה psula to the
other brothers.
No, if there's no other brothers.
If there's no other brothers, then that's exactly what the גמרא Gemara
says, right? The גמרא Gemara says ולחלוץ
שלא
במקום אחין. velachalotz shelo bemakom achin. Right? רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would
say there's no point. Why should Should she do חליצה chalitzah and
maybe become אסורה assurah to a כהן cohen or something like that?
Just don't bother. He's a סריס. saris. It's not going to make
a difference. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda would say
sure go ahead. What's the what do you have to lose? If
he's a male, if he's a fertile male, then the חליצה chalitzah
counts. If he's not, then there's no חליצה chalitzah anyway. And it
all works out. So that's the those are the bases of their
מחלוקת. machloket.
Is there a question? No. Good. אמר רב שמואל בר יהודה אמר
רבי אבא, Amar Rav Shmuel bar Yehuda amar Rabbi Abba, אחוה ד
רבי יהודה בר זבדי אמר רב. achuh d'Rabbi Yehuda bar Zavdi amar
Rav. Well, long train of tradition in the name of רב. Rav.
Oh sorry, אמר רב יהודה אמר רב. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav.
אנדרוגינוס חייבין עליו סקילה משתי מקומות. Androgynos chayavin alav skila mishtei mekomot.
We're back to the the question of the hermaphrodite and whether or
not you are חייב chayav for both kinds of sexual intercourse which
we said yesterday is both anal and vaginal, although you'll see in
the language here is I don't know challenging for me.
And so the רב Rav says yes,
an
אנדרוגינוס androgynos you're חייב סקילה chayav skila for both of those for
either of those kinds of of sex. מיתיבי, Meitivei, we have a
ברייתא. braita. רבי אליעזר אומר אנדרוגינוס חייבין עליו סקילה כבזכר. Rabbi Eliezer
omer androgynos chayavin alav skila k'vizachar.
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says that the אנדרוגינוס androgynos is like a
man and therefore it should only be the male way, meaning we
said yesterday anally. במה דברים אמורים, Bameh devarim amurim, בזכרות שלו, bizchrut
shelo, in the male way. Again
it's very hard for me to interpret בזכרות שלו bizchrut shelo as
as anal but I don't know that seems to be the that
seems to be the direction we're going for the reason that Dov
said yesterday that it's obvious that penetrating another male would be would
be אסור. assur. אבל בנקבות שלו פטור. Aval b'nikvut shelo patur. ההוא
ד Hahu d'
so we say this רב Rav says הוא דאמר כי האי תנא.
hu d'amar ki hai tanna. דתניא, Detanya, רבי סימאי אומר אנדרוגינוס חייבין
עליו סקילה משתי מקומות. Rabbi Simai omer androgynos chayavin alav skila mishtei
mekomot.
רב Rav is not is רב Rav isn't in trouble, not that
רב Rav would be in so much trouble anyway because we when
רב Rav gets into this kind of trouble we'll say רב תנא
הוא ופליג. Rav tanna hu u'palig. But in this case רב Rav
is not in trouble because he has another ברייתא. braita. He has
רבי סימאי Rabbi Simai who says that indeed a טומטום tumtum sorry
an אנדרוגינוס androgynos you're חייב סקילה chayav skila for
both for for having sex in both ways. מאי טעמא דרבי סימאי?
Mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Simai? What's the the basis for רבי סימאי's Rabbi
Simai position? אמר רבא בר המדורי, Amar Rava bar Hamdurei, אסברה לי,
asbrah li, it was explained to me. ואת זכר לא תשכב משכבי
אשה. V'et zachar lo tishkav mishkevei ishah.
So the literally the the פסוק pasuk that talks about that that
says that homosexual sex is is not allowed says you shall not
lay you shall not lay with a male the lyings of a
woman. So he says איזהו זכר שיש בו שני משכבות? Eizehu zachar
sheyesh bo shenei mishkavot? How what's what kind of man can have
lyings several different kinds? הוי אומר זה אנדרוגינוס. Hevei omer zeh androgynos.
This we're talking about this this פסוק pasuk is specifically talking about
a hermaphrodite.
Wait so is he saying that well then and then קל וחומר
kal vachomer to a regular guy? In other words where where do
you get
the the איסור issur for? You're asking the you're asking the right
questions. You're asking exactly the right questions. The גמרא Gemara will get
to it. ורבנן אף על גב דאית ביה שתי משכבות, V'rabbanan af
al gav d'it beih shetei mishkavot, את זכר כתיב. et zachar ketiv.
It says את זכר, et zachar, a man should not lie that
way as and therefore we're talking about by way of his זכרות
zachrut says רש"י, Rashi, right? In the in the male way. And
then
you
asked what the משכבי mishkevei means.
So okay ורבנן, v'rabbanan,
זכר גרידא מנלהו? zachar gerida minalhu? No the רבנן rabbanan might agree
with the משכבי mishkevei saying oh yeah that is שתי מקומות. shtei
mekomot. But even though it says שתי מקומות, shtei mekomot, right? we
say את זכר. et zachar. We're talking about an אנדרוגינוס androgynos according
to the רבנן, rabbanan, but we have a פסוק pasuk that says
although there are two משכבות, mishkavot, one of them is one of
them is a
what's
it called only one of them is אסור, assur, the other one
is פטור. patur.
So we say okay well what about just a straightforward homosexual relationship
then? Or I should say sexual relationship then?
מנלהו? Minalhu? מאשה. Me'ishah.
This is it starts to get very very complicated exactly what the
מדרש midrash is doing here. But the רבנן rabbanan learn from the
extra word משכבי אשה, mishkevei ishah, right? What could it have said?
It could have just said do not lie with a man. Why
does it say משכבי אשה, mishkevei ishah, the word אשה ishah at
the end of at the end there? Oh from that we learn
even just a single normal homosexual intercourse.
How do you get that from אשה? ishah?
So you don't need You don't need to have a specific semantic
connection to the word אשה. Isha. אשה Isha is an extra word
and that and therefore that's what they're going to learn from it.
So we say okay, but what about באשה שלא כדרכה? Beisha Shelo
Kedarka? There is a principle that anybody who
you're אסור assur to have sex with, you can't have either anal
or vaginal sex, even with a woman. And we normally learn that
from the fact that it says משכבי אשה, Mishkvei Isha, the lyings
of a woman. So now that you've decided that the word משכבי
Mishkvei is in reference to a טומטום, tumtum, what happened where do
we get the... sorry
yes and אנדרוגינוס... androgynous... how where do we get the case of
anal sex with a woman that that would actually be a sexual,
that would count as an אסור assur sexual intercourse? So מנא להו?
minaluhu? So מו'אשה. mi veisha. It appears, I looked into it as
far as I could, I tried to understand what was going on
here, it appears that it says ואת זכר לא תשכב משכבי אשה,
Ve'et Zachar Lo Tishkav Mishkvei Isha, and somehow the combination of the
ו vav in the beginning and the אשה Isha at the end
creates this extra thing. I don't, it's very hard for me to
understand. The only other way I can understand it is that we
have ואשה אל אחתה לא תקח לצרר לגלות ערותה עליה בחייה. Ve'isha
El Achotah Lo Tikach Litzror Legalot Ervatah Aleha Bechayeha. There's in the
same פרשה parsha that discusses homosexuality, there's also a discussion, or I
should, I have to, you know, it's very easy to say the
wrong thing, it discusses homosexual sex. In that same פרשה parsha it
says that you shouldn't take, marry a woman and her sister and
it uses the word ואשה. Ve'isha.
So perhaps it's trying to learn from that פסוק pasuk that that
extra ו vav there, why does it have ואשה, Ve'isha, why doesn't
it just say אשה? Isha? I don't know, it's not clear to
me. What is clear that there are certain נוסחים, nusachim, the ב"ח
Bach mentions it and the מסורת הש"ס Masoret Hashas also mentions it,
that say ואת אשה, Ve'et Isha, and frankly I'm not familiar with
a פסוק pasuk that starts ואת אשה. Ve'et Isha. Charlie?
Might it just be one of those cases where they had a
tradition that knew it had to be a דאורייתא d'oraitha prohibition and
they were just trying to justify it, we see that other places?
It could be, you just would hope that they would come up
with something that was a little more obvious in terms of what
are they even talking about here? Are they talking about the ו
vav in ואת זכר? Ve'et Zachar? The way that שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz understood
it was ואת זכר לא תשכב משכבי אשה Ve'et Zachar Lo Tishkav
Mishkvei Isha and it's the ו vav from ואת Ve'et and the
אשה Isha at the end. It's a very strange way of presenting
it here if that's the case.
אמר רב שיזבי אמר רב חסדא. Amar Rav Shizbi, amar Rav Chisda.
לא לכל אמר רבי אליעזר אנדרוגינוס זכר מעליא. Lo lekol amar Rabbi
Eliezer androgunus zachar ma'alya. Rabbi Eliezer didn't say that an אנדרוגינוס androgynous
is a full male for
everything, הוא שאם אתה אומר כן במוקדשים יקדש. hu she'im attah omer
ken bemo kodeshim yikdash. Because if you were to say such a
thing, then if somebody were to try to bring a sacrifice from
an אנדרוגינוס androgynous animal, a hermaphroditic animal, it would still be a
case of קודש. kodesh.
So we say ומנלן דלא קדש? uminalan d'lo kadash? How do we
know that it doesn't work? דתנו רבנן. Detanu Rabbanan. We have a
ברייתא. baraita. הנרבע, Hanirba, somebody that an animal that was used for
a bestial sexual relationship by a man. Sorry,
yes, that's right. והמוקצה, Vehamuktzeh, and an animal that was taken aside
and laid aside specially for עבודה זרה avodah zarah even if it
wasn't used. והנעבד, Ve'hane'evad, and an animal that was actually worshipped. והאתנן,
Veha'etnan, and an animal that was purchased with the fee of a
prostitute.
ומחיר, Umchir, ומחיר mchir is sort of the other direction, the an
animal that was purchased with the price of either an actual dog,
it says אתנן זונה ומחיר כלב לא תביא בית אלהיך, etnan zonah
umchir kelev lo tavi beit elokecha, that you can't bring either a
prostitute or the price of a dog.
Biblical scholars tell us that כלב kelev is a way that they
referred to male prostitutes at that time. I'm not sure whether
the גמרא Gemara views it. My recollection is that the גמרא Gemara
actually thinks of it as an actual dog. Yeah.
In any case, וטומטום ואנדרוגינוס
מטמאים בגדים בבית הבליעה. vetumtum ve'androgunus mitammim begadim beit habliah. We're talking
here about birds, which have a very specific rule that if you
eat נבלת עוף, nivlat oph, a bird that has died not from
שחיטה, shechita,
then it מטמא בגדים, mitameh begadim, it causes your clothes to become
טמא tamei as soon as you put it into the... to your
mouth.
So what this means is let's say you try to bring these
birds to the Temple. In the Temple you know you don't שחט
shecht birds, you do מליקה, melika, you break their neck from the
back. So if, if, if it's not an animal that is מותר
mutar for,
for bringing to the Temple, then when you do the מליקה, melika,
it's not a כשר שחיטה kosher shechita and therefore what you have
is a נבילה. neveila. So all of these things are אסור asur
for קדשים kodashim and therefore when you do מליקה, melika, it's a
נבילה neveila and therefore it causes- it causes you to be מטמא
בגדים. metame begadim. Yes.
I think it's the throat that it- it's when it reaches the
throat.
When it reaches the throat, that is to say when you swallow
it. בית הבליעה. beit hablia. Okay, that's fine.
I think. I mean that's what it meant.
That's fine. I actually didn't check into it very much, so excuse
me for saying the wrong thing. רבי אליעזר אומר טומטום ואנדרוגינוס אין
מטמאין בגדים בית הבליעה. Rabbi Eliezer omer tumtum ve'androgynus ein metamin begadim
beit hablia. So
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says actually these animals- these birds are not
מטמא, metame, which is interesting because רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer if- if
that's true, then רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer apparently thinks that these birds
actually are acceptable in some sense for the קדשים kodashim and therefore
you can-
hold on one second.
He seems to think that a טומטום tumtum or an אנדרוגינוס androgynus
bird is acceptable for קדשים kodashim and therefore when you do מליקה
melika it's not a נבילה. neveila. So that seems to be proving
the opposite
of what we just saw. But we have a continuation. שהיה רבי
אליעזר אומר. shehaya Rabbi Eliezer omer. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer had the
following principle: כל מקום שנאמר זכר ונקבה אתה מוציא טומטום ואנדרוגינוס מביניהם
ועוף הואיל
ולא נאמר בו זכר ונקבה אי אתה מוציא טומטום ואנדרוגינוס מביניהם.
kol makom shenemar zachar unekeva ata motzi tumtum ve'androgynus mibeineihem ve'of ho'il
velo ne'emar bo zachar unekeva i ata motzi tumtum ve'androgynus mibeineihem. By
four-legged animals, whenever we talk about the sacrifices, we talk about-
we talk about what gender you bring. שה זכר תמים seh zachar
tamim or שה נקבה, seh nekeva, כבשה kivsa or something like that.
Yes, Charlie?
For שלמים shlamim it doesn't matter, you could bring a male or
a female.
Yes, but it still I think discusses which-
I don't know, I don't remember.
It seems to me that it still uses the terms זכר ונקבה,
zachar unekeva,
which and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says- the truth is it's not
that important whether this is true of all cases of four-legged animals
or just in the case of the ones where it actually says
which- which gender you need to bring, but it certainly says that
in a case where there's gender mentioned, you certainly can't bring it
as a קודש, kodesh, and therefore it must be the case that
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer doesn't hold that an אנדרוגינוס androgynus is a
זכר לכל, zachar lakol, right? It's not always considered to be male.
Yeah, I got- I got the verse, yeah. זכרים אם זכר אם
נקבה
zcharim im zachar im
nekeva for שלמים. shlamim.
Right.
אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק. amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak. So a
new statement. אף אנן נמי תנינא. af anan nami tanina. I also
have a משנה mishna that says this. Interesting point about רב נחמן
בר יצחק, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, he sees himself- he says in
one place, 'I'm not a- I don't say big חידושים, chidushim, I'm
not a big- I don't say lots of laws or those kind
of things. What do I do? I organize, I cross-reference.' So in
many, many cases we find רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak saying אף אנן נמי תנינא, af anan nami tanina, I also
have a משנה mishna that can represent this, not just a ברייתא.
braita. רבי אליעזר אומר
הכלאים וטריפה ויוצא דופן טומטום ואנדרוגינוס לא קדושים ולא מקדשים. Rabbi Eliezer
omer hakilayim utreifa ve'yotzei dofen tumtum ve'androgynus lo kedoshim velo makdishim.
So the cases of an animal that is a hybrid, like- I
can't think- not sure what a hybrid cow species would be that-
or a hybrid animal that you could bring to the מקדש. Mikdash.
A cross between a goat and a sheep. Oh, okay, there you
go.
Which when we were in חולין Chullin we laughed at that as
a possibility and then we discovered there actually have been such.
Okay.
Or a טריפה, treifa, an animal that is fatally wounded or fatally
ill but not yet dead.
ויוצא דופן, veyotzei dofen, an animal that was born by cesarean section.
טומטום ואנדרוגינוס, tumtum ve'androgynus, לא קדושים, lo kedoshim, they don't become קודש,
kodesh, ולא מקדישים, velo makdishim, and they don't make other things קודש.
kodesh. So what are we talking about? Like they're nothing.
Yes, they don't- they don't have any standing in the קודש kodesh
world. ואמר שמואל לא קדושים בתמורה ולא מקדישים בעושה תמורה שמע מינה.
ve'amar Shmuel lo kedoshim bitmura velo makdishim be'osei tmura shma mina. What's
the case that we're talking about? שמואל Shmuel says it's the case
of trying to do תמורה, tmura, trying to swap things. So you
know that in cases
of where you have something that's קודש, kodesh, you cannot- you can't
say, 'I would rather have this- I have this cow which I've
made...' dedicated to be a קרבן, Korban, but the truth is I'd
really like to have this cow for myself. What I'm going to
do is I'm going to take the, I'm going not going to
bring this cow, I'm going to bring that cow instead. What ends
up happening is that this cow is still קודש, Kodesh, and the
cow over here now also is קודש. Kodesh. That's the rules by
תמורה. Temura. So, let's say that you have a cow that you
want to be, that is going is dedicated to a קרבן, Korban,
and you say, "I'm not going to bring this cow for a
קרבן, Korban, instead I'm going to bring this hermaphroditic cow that over
here that I
have." So, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer according to the position of שמואל
Shmuel says, nothing happened. There's no the that hermaphroditic cow did not
become קודש Kodesh in any way.
And the same goes in the other direction. Let's say you have
a קודש Kodesh hermaphrodite cow and you- "You can do that?" So,
good question. So רש"י Rashi discusses it. Let's say you have
a- "But because
of the mother maybe, because you מקדש mekadesh the mother then this
is born as a hermaphrodite."
Very good.
So you have a mother that is קודש Kodesh and it gives
birth to a hermaphrodite, so the hermaphrodite is also
קודש. Kodesh.
"What do you do with it?"
So it's, it's ירעה עד שיסתאב. yireh ad sheyista-ev. It wanders around
until it gets a מום mum and then you can use it
for whatever you want.
"Hermaphrodite is אנדרוגינוס?" Androgynos?
Yes, אנדרוגינוס Androgynos is a hermaphrodite.
"And and אנדרוגינוס Androgynos wouldn't be
automatically
a מום?"
mum? No, it's not considered to be a מום. mum. So when
you say, you know, the קודש Kodesh of this cow and I
want to put the קודש Kodesh onto this cow, nothing happens. Doesn't
work for anything.
And therefore we learn that indeed רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer doesn't consider
the אנדרוגינוס Androgynos to be a זכר לכל. zachar lakol.
רבי אליעזר אומר חייבין עליו סקילה כזכר. Rabbi Eliezer omer chayavin alav
skila kezachar. It's funny we've discussed this line so many times you'd
think that we'd already discussed it
in the גמרא, Gemara, but now the גמרא Gemara comes to that
פסקא. piska. תניא. Tanya. We have a ברייתא braita that says: אמר
רבי כשהלכתי ללמוד תורה אצל רבי אלעזר בן שמוע חברו עליו תלמידיו
כתרנגולים של בית בוקיא ולא הניחוני ללמוד. Amar Rabbi kshehalachti lilmod Torah
etzel Rabbi Elazar ben Shamoa chavru alav talmidav ketarnigolim shel beit bukya
velo hinichuni lilmod. So רבי Rabbi says, "I had this experience. I
went to learn by רבי אלעזר בן שמוע, Rabbi Elazar ben Shamoa,
who's the רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar the student of רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva who I mentioned before.
And his students were so aggressive and they gathered around me so
aggressively, they were like the the roosters from the בית בוקיא, Beit
Bukya, which רש"י Rashi tells us is this place where they have
very aggressive
roosters, and they wouldn't let me learn." It's interesting, I'm trying to
decide, I mean you can't really tell, but it's interesting whether רבי
Rabbi was sort of a minor celebrity because he was sort of
next in line to be the
נשיא, Nasi, and you know, they were so excited that רבי Rabbi
had come to visit them that they just kept on pestering him
all the time, or if they were so protective of their relationship
with
רבי אלעזר בן שמוע Rabbi Elazar ben Shamoa that they kind of
blocked him out and they wouldn't let him get close. I'm not
sure what's going on here, but it is interesting to hear these
sort of first-hand accounts of the kind of stuff that happened.
"Well it's also funny because we were talking about like an עוף,
of, you know just a second ago."
Right, and now we're talking about תרנגולים דבית בוקיא. tarnigolim d'beit bukya.
Good point.
"That's I saw a photo of roosters
fighting."
Okay, listen that's, he
has... ולא הניחוני ללמוד אלא דבר אחד במשנתנו רבי אליעזר אומר אנדרוגינוס
חייבין עליו סקילה כזכר. Velo hinichuni lilmod ela davar echad bemishnatenu Rabbi
Eliezer omer Androgynos chayavin alav skila kezachar. The hermaphrodite, you're חייב עליו
chayav alav for him like a like a male. הדרן עלך הערל.
Hadran alach He-arel. And that's the end of הערל. He-arel. I think
I began הערל He-arel and I think I finished it, I just
didn't learn any of the middle.
Okay, we have about fifteen more minutes.
I have to admit that
I didn't have the opportunity to prepare the next משנה, Mishnah, but
we can at least start it and go on.
I feel bad because "I can do the next."
"You can do it?" "Yeah."
"Okay. Although there's a long רש"י Rashi here which I didn't get
to the bottom of at the end, so maybe I'll follow up
with that
tomorrow." יש מותרות לבעליהן ואסורות ליבמיהן. Yesh mutarot l'valeihen va-asurot liyvameihen. There
are those some women who are permitted to their husbands but they
are forbidden to, if the husband dies, to the brother, to the
יבם. yavam. "I thought you said you had to go by the-"
"You want to stay, that's okay." יש מותרות ליבמיהן ואסורות לבעליהן. Yesh
mutarot liyvameihen va-asurot l'valeihen. Some cases they're permitted to the brother-in-law, but
they are forbidden to their husband in the first place. We'll see
what the משנה Mishnah is going to give examples of all of
these. מותרות לאלו ולאלו. mutarot l'elu ul'elu. Of course there are some
women, most women, who are permitted to both the husband...